We've already talked about access and modifies in tight script classes and in this lesson
we're going to expand upon our knowledge even further.
So TypeScript has a way of controlling which parts of a class are visible and accessible.
We're going to already learn about public and provide it and we also are going to learn
about protected which is used to enforce encapsulation and protect internal state and only
expose what's necessary.
So in terms of a class that are three access modifiers, public, private and protected.
So the public which this code shows here is the default and that allows us to access
the code from anywhere we like.
So in this code here as an example we set up a public property here as well as a public
method and that allows us then to access the code anywhere we want to.
Now what about if you want to have just internal information, so now it's paste in example.
So we have a bank account, now this is obviously we don't want anyone's access to balance
directly.
We have to use some approved methods, so we've now specified private on this property
here and we have these two individual methods and again don't forget that if it's not
actually specifically mentioned is public then these by default are going to be made public.
So we can now create an instance of that particular class, let's say const account equals
new bank account.
And if we try to access the balance directly, we can't specify it, we have to of course
use the two approved members.
So private members are only accessible inside the class itself, which is great for protecting
internal state.
So now we've talked about public and we talked about private, so this just leaves us with
the other access modifier which is protected.
So protected allows our members inside our class to be accessible within the class and
also any class that inherits from it but not outside if it doesn't inherit from it.
So I'm just going to do a little example, let's have a class of animal, we're going
to have a protected property called sound, which is going to be string and just set it
to a generic sound on this particular animal, that's up a public method called make a sound.
It's going to return a string and just simply do this sound.
Now we're going to create the second class and the second class is going to extend the
animal class and we're going to define a method called bark, which is a public method,
which returns a string, we say return our return dog says dollar, this dot sound.
So this sound of course is inheriting from our animal class.
Now this is absolutely fine because we can access this because the dog is inheriting
from our animal class.
But if we try to create an instance of the animal class itself, let's do var my animal equals
new animal and now we're going to try and access that property sound we can't because
we are doing it, we're not actually inheriting from the animal directly.
So access modifiers allow us us to control visibility and protect our class logics.